#### UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO SCHOOL OF MEDICINE

# Drew E. Winters, PhD. drew.winters@cuanschutz.edu

## Biographical sketch

Drew E. Winters, PhD. is a post-doctoral fellow at the University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus In the department of Psychiatry under the Developmental Psychobiology and Behavior T32 program. His research focuses on brain and behavior mechanisms underlying neurocognitive and socio-affective processes with an emphasis on adolescents with callous-unemotional traits. In this vein, this work aims to identify replicable neural mechanisms that may improve development and testing of interventions for youth with callous-unemotional traits.

Education			
University of Colorado Anschutz Me - Post-Doctoral Fellow: Develo Research Group (DPRG) - Primary mentor: Dr. Joseph S	Current		
Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN.			April 2020
Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN. – MSW			May 2016
Purdue University, Fort Wayne, IN. – B.S.			May 2013
Certifications			
Machine Learning Using Scikit-Learn in Python – Inira			May 2022
Data Scientist in Python - DataCamp			Nov 2021
Computational Neuroscience – Neur	Computational Neuroscience – Neuromatch Academy		
Data Scientist in R – DataCamp	Data Scientist in R – DataCamp		
Multilevel Modeling II Advanced Topics – EITM			Oct 2020
Network Analysis II Advanced Topic	cs – EITM		Oct 2020
Structural Equation Modeling with L	atent Variab	les – EITM	Oct 2018
Academic appointments			
University of Colorado	Statistician	School evaluation	2021-2022
University of Colorado	Post-Doctor	ral Fellow	2020-Present
Indiana University	Adjunct Professor		2017-2020
University of Michigan	Teaching A	ssistant	2019 & 2020
Indiana University SOM	Research Analyst		2018-2020
Indiana University SOM	Research A		2016-2020
Indiana University	Research A	ssistant	2014-2015
Hospital, government, or other profession	onal positio	ns	
UCHealth Encompass program - Au		Therapist	2020-2021
Family Works Inc Indianapolis, IN	T	Therapist	2016-2020
Rogers behavioral health – Skokie II	_	Behavioral Therapist	2014-2016
Honors, special recognitions, and award	ls		

2021

2021

Postdoctoral Association Travel Award

University of Colorado, Aurora, CO

Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models – Statistics Mastery

Multilevel Modeling II: Advanced Topics Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models – S Network Analysis II: Advanced Topics	2021		
Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models – S Structural Equation Modeling with Latent Mod	2018		
Developmental, Child, and Family Psychology For ICPSR Quantitative Methods of Social Research	2018		
Indiana University Travel Fellow	,	2017-2019	
Graduate Professional Student Government Fellowship		2016	
Miranda Pang Endowment	•		
Phi Kappa Phi: Academic Honor Society		2013	
Tau Upsilon Alpha: Human Services Academic F	2013		
Hellen I. and Rodney E. Nern Scholarship	·	2013	
Membership in professional organizations			
Society for the Scientific Study of Psychopathy (		2022-current	
Society of Clinical Child and Adolescent Psychol	logy	2020-current	
Society for Social Work and Research (SSWR)		2017-current	
M-1 C14 1 C1- D1-114			
Major Committee and Service Responsibilities	hal and athan Dunas	2011 2019	
Board of Directors, National Association of Alco	•	2011-2018	
of Abuse Counselors, Indiana Chapter, Indianapo	711S, 11N		
Licensure and board certification			
License	Certified	Recertified	
Licensed Social Worker – Colorado	7/2020	7/2021	
Licensed Social Worker – Indiana	7/2016	8/2019	
Review and referee work			
Ad Hoc Reviewer			
Neuroimage		2022	
Emotion		2022	
Journal of Drug Issues	2022		
Addictive Behaviors Reports		2022	
Brain Imaging and Behavior		2022	
Cerebral Cortex		2021	
Neuroscience Letters		2021	
Psychophysiology	2021		
Journal of Drug and Alcohol Dependence	2021		
Journal of Juvenile Justice	2018		
Journal of Child and Family Studies	2017		
Mindfulness		2016	

# **Open-Source Software Packages**

**resmod.** A python package that derives interaction terms using centered residuals <a href="https://pypi.org/project/resmod/">https://pypi.org/project/resmod/</a>, role: author

**fsub\_extractor.** A python package that ties diffusion and functional brain data together. <a href="https://github.com/smeisler/fsub\_extractor">https://github.com/smeisler/fsub\_extractor</a>, role: contributor

Invited extramural lectures, presentations and visiting professorships

Winters, D.E., Sakai, J.T., Carter, R.M., Computational Lesioning of Heterogenous Functional Connectomes Explains Variance in Adolescent Callous-Unemotional Traits. Neurohackadamy, University of Washington, Seattle, WA	July 2022
Sanchez, C.R., Cooley, J.L., <b>Winters, D.E.</b> , Ricker, B.T., & Fite, P.J. <i>Prospective associations between forms of aggression and peer victimization: The moderating role of prosocial behavior</i> . Biennial Research Conference on Relational Aggression, Virtual Conference.	July 2022
<b>Winters, D.E.</b> , <i>Introduction to R for medical students</i> . University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, CO	April 2022
Winters, D.E., Cognitive Load Sensitivity Impacts Theory of Mind Impairments in Callous-Unemotional Traits. Developmental Psychobiology Research Group, Denver, CO	April 2022
Winters, D.E., Affective Theory of Mind Impairments in Youth with Callous-Unemotional Traits: The Role of Cognitive Control. American College of Neuropsychopharmacology. San Juan, PR	Dec 12/2021
Winters, D.E., Network typology of adolescents with callous- unemotional traits. Department of Psychiatry Poster Session, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, CO	March 2021
<b>Winters, D.E.</b> , Adolescent Prosocial Behavior and Affective Theory of Mind: The Role of Cognitive Control and Callousness.  Developmental Psychobiology Research Group, Denver, CO	March 2021
<b>Winters, D.E.</b> , <i>Longitudinal Data Analysis Using Secondary Data</i> . S728 multivariate statistics, Dr. Sadaaki Fukui. Indiana University School of Social Work, Indianapolis, IN.	Jan 2021
<b>Winters, D.E.</b> , <i>Neural Connectivity of Empathy and its Impairments in Adolescents</i> . Developmental Psychobiology Research Group, Denver, CO	Oct 2020
<b>Winters, D.E.</b> , <i>Statistical Approaches of Propensity Score Matching</i> . Training the Indiana Department of Children Services data analysis and evaluation team, Indianapolis, IN.	March 2020
<b>Winters, D.E.</b> , <i>Secondary data analysis</i> . S728 multivariate statistics, Dr. Sadaaki Fukui. Indiana University School of Social Work, Indianapolis, IN.	Jan 2020
Winters, D.E. Mindfulness and Acceptance and Commitment Therapy in Clinical Practice. Advanced clinical practice, Dr. Vincent Starnino, instructor. Indiana University School of Social Work, Indianapolis, IN.	June 2017
<b>Winters</b> , <b>D.E</b> . <i>Mindfulness in Addictions Treatment</i> . Presentation to staff and clients at the Life Recovery Center, Indianapolis, IN.	Aug 2016
Winters, D.E. Mindfulness in Clinician Self-Care, and Clinical Practice. Presented to the staff and honor society recipients of Chi Eta Sigma for marriage and family therapist. Purdue University, Fort Wayne, IN.	April 2016

	adiana University School of Social Work – Teaching A S623 Practice Research Integrative Seminar	Assistant Online	Summer 2017
	S623 Practice Research Integrative Seminar	Online	Spring 2017
	S623 Practice Research Integrative Seminar	Seminar	Fall 2016
	niversity of Michigan – ICPSR		
	Regression Analysis II: Linear models	Online	Summer 2020
]	Regression Analysis II: Linear models	Seminar	Summer 2019
	ndiana University– Adjunct Professor		
	S728 Advanced Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Spring 2020
	S718 Intermediate Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Fall 2019
	S728 Advanced Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Spring 2019
,	S718 Intermediate Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Fall 2018
;	S517 Assessment in Mental Health & Addictions	Seminar	Summer 2018
Ment	toring		
	Neuromatch Academy – Computational Neuroscience Mentor  - I mentored a group of five participants in the computational neuroscience track on completing capstone project.		2022
	Gabriel Yepes, M.D. – Research Mentor  - I mentored Dr. Yepes on conducting research armanuscripts resulting in one research publication	nd writing	2021
Grant support  Developmental Psychobiology Endowment Fund. Project title: 'The effects of cognitive load on prosocial behavior amongst early adolescents with high callous-unemotional traits and typically developing controls.' Funding amount \$7,220 Role: PI		2021 – 2022	
	National Institutes of Mental Health T32MH015442-42; Laudenslager, Mark (PI), Developmental Psychopathology, Psychobiology & Behavior. <u>Role</u> : Postdoctoral Fellow		2020 – present
	Indiana Department of Children Services Title IV-E Wa 13-4F-C0-0981; Pierce, Barbra (PI), Indiana University Medicine. Role: Research Analyst		2019 – 2020
	Indiana Department of Children Services Title IV-E Wa 13-4F-C0-0981; Hall, Jim (PI), Indiana University Scho Medicine. Role: Research Assistant		2017 – 2019

# **Bibliography**

# **Published**

## **Published Peer-Reviewed Articles**

Richie-Halford, A., Cieslak, M., Ai, L., Caffarra, S., Covitz, S., Franco, A.R., Karipidis, I.I., Kruper, J., Milham, M., Avelar-Pereira, B., Roy, E., Sydnor, V.J., Yeatman, J.D., The Fibr Community Science Consortium (**Drew E. Winters**), Theodore D. Satterthwaite, Ariel Rokem (2022) An analysis-ready and quality controlled resource for pediatric brain white-matter research. Scientific Data, 9(1): p. 616.

- **Winters, D.E.**, Hyde, L. W. (2022). Shared Functional Network Connectivity Between Callous-Unemotionality and both Cognitive and Affective Empathy. *Journal of Affective Disorders*.
- **Winters, D.E.**, Sakai, J.T. (2022) Emotion identification for self and other associated with callous-unemotional traits and sex differences in early adolescents. *Child Psychiatry & Human Development*.
- **Winters, D.E.,** Pruitt P. J., Damoiseaux J.S, Sakai, J.T. (2021). Moderating effect of CU traits on functional connectivity underlying empathy in adolescents. *Psychiatry Research Neuroimaging*. DOI: 10.1016/j.pscychresns.2021.111429
- **Winters D.E.**, Sakai, J.T., Carston, R.M. (2021) Resting-state network topology characterizing callous-unemotional traits in adolescence. Neuroimage: Clinical, 2021: p. 102878.
- **Winters, D.E.,** Susan M., Hopfer, C., Sakai, J.T. (2021). Moderating effects of CU traits on transdiagnostic symptoms association with suicidality in adolescents. *Child Psychiatry and Human Development*. DOI: 10.1007/s10578-021-01256-w
- **Winters D.E.**, Pruitt P. J., Fukui S., Cyders M.A., Pierce B. J., Lay K., Damoiseaux J.S. (2021). Indirect paths between functional connectivity underlying heterogenous depression symptoms in adolescents via cognitive and affective empathy. *Child Psychiatry and Human Development*. DOI: 10.1007/s10578-021-01242-2
- Winters, D.E., Pruit P.J., Fukui, S., Cyders, M. A., Pierce, B. J., Lay, K., Damoiseaux, J. S. (2021). Network functional connectivity underlying dissociable cognitive and affective components of empathy in adolescence. *Neuropsychologia*. DOI: 10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2021.107832
- **Winters, D.E.**, Brandon-Friedman, R., Yepes, G., Hinkley, J. (2020). Systematic review and meta-analysis of socio-cognitive and socio-affective processes association with adolescent substance use. *Drug and Alcohol Dependence*. DOI: 10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.108479
- Winters, D.E., Pierce, B. J., Imburgia, T. (2020) Concrete services usage on child placement stability: Propensity score matched effects. *Child and Youth Service Review*. DOI: 10.1016/j.childyouth.2020.105362
- **Winters, D.E.**, Wu, W., Fukui, S. (2020). Longitudinal effects of cognitive and affective empathy on adolescent substance use. *Substance Use & Misuse*, 1-7. DOI: 10.1080/10826084.2020.1717537
- Winters, D.E., Fukui, S., Leibenluft, E., Hulvershorn L.A., (2018). Improvements in Irritability with Open-Label Methylphenidate in Youth with Comorbid Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder and Disruptive Mood Dysregulation Disorder. *Journal of Child and Adolescent Psychopharmacology*, 28(5): 298-305.
- Beerbower, E., **Winters, D.E.**, Kondrat, D. (2018). Bio-psycho-social-spiritual needs of adolescents and young adults with life-threatening illnesses: Implications for social work practice. *Social Work in Health Care*, 1-17. DOI: 10.1080/00981389.2018.1430091
- Winters, D.E., Beerbower, E. (2017). Mindfulness and Meditation as an Adjunctive Treatment for Adolescents Involved in the Juvenile Justice System: Is Repairing the Brain and Nervous System Possible? *Social Work in Health Care*, 1-21. Doi:10.1080/00981389.2017.1316341

Armstrong, E., **Winters, D.E.**, Jaggers, J. (2018). Mental Health in Prison Populations. Serving the Stigmatized: Working within the Incarcerated Environment. W.T. Church and D.W. Springer, Oxford University Press.

### Technical Reports for the State of Indiana

Winters, D.E., Imburgia, T., Pierce, B. J. (2017, 2018, 2019, 2020). Concrete Services Spending and outcomes for youth. Indiana Department of Child Services Child Welfare Title IV-E Waiver Demonstration Project Extension: Final Report.

#### **Unpublished**

#### Under Review

- **Winters, D.E.**, Sakai, J.T. (under review). Cognitive processes underlying prosocial decision making in callous-unemotional traits.
- **Winters, D.E.**, Sakai, J.T. (under review). Affective theory of mind impairments underlying callous-unemotional traits and the role of cognitive control: A pilot study.
- **Winters, D.E.**, Massey, S.H., Sakai, J.T. (under review). Adolescent substance use outcomes in response to social consequences of use: the role of empathy.
- **Winters, D.E.**, Sakai, J.T. (under review). Prosocial behavior limitations associated with callous-unemotional traits are moderated by internalizing symptoms
- Sakai, J.T., Chintaluru, Y., Raymond, K., McWilliams, S., Carter, R., **Winters, D.E.**, Mikulich, S. (under review). Can Moral Elevation Response Increase Prosocial Behavior? Examining the Effects of Psychopathic Traits.
- **Winters, D.E.**, Sakai, J.T. (under review) Callous-Unemotional traits association with prosocial behavior and the mediating role of cognitive control.
- **Winters, D.E.**, Leopold, D.R., Sakai, J.T., Carter, R.M. (under review) Resting-state connectivity underlying cognitive control's association with perspective taking in callous-unemotional traits.

## In preparation

- Winters, D.E., Leopold, D.R., Sakai, J.T., Carter, R.M. Efficiency of heterogenous functional connectomes explains variance in callous-unemotional traits after computational lesioning cortical midline and salience regions
- **Winters, D.E.**, Sakai, J.T. Connectome-based predictive modeling of empathy in adolescents with and without the low-prosocial emotion specifier
- **Winters, D.E.**, Connectome-based data-driven subgroups association with theoretical groups of callous-unemotional traits and low prosocial emotion specifier